20世紀福斯  夢工廠影業
聯合奉獻
紮努克公司  出品
領銜主演: 湯姆·漢克斯
領銜主演: 保羅·紐曼
領銜主演: 裘德·洛
{\fnMicrosoft YaHei\fs28\bord1\shad1\4a&H80&\b0片名: 毀 滅 之 路
There are many stories about Michael Sullivan.
麥克·蘇利文的故事多到說不完
Some say he was a decent man.
有人說他為人正直
Some say there was no good in him at all.
有人說他一無是處
But I once spent six weeks on the road with him...
1931年冬天  我曾和他一同旅行
...in the winter of 1931.
六個星期
This is our story.
這是我們的故事
主演: 詹妮弗·傑森·李
主演: 斯坦利·圖齊
主演: 丹尼爾·克雷格
Thank you, sir. Much obliged. Man dies in factory accident!
謝謝  感謝您  工廠奪命意外
{\fnMicrosoft YaHei\fs24\bord1\shad1\4a&H80&\pos(192,40)\b0主演: 泰勒·霍奇林
Get your paper here! Hot off the press, only 5 cents!
買份快報  剛出版的  只要五分錢
主演: 連姆·艾肯   狄倫·貝克   塞倫·希德
選角: 黛布拉·贊恩
本片改編自同名繪本小說   作者:馬克斯·艾倫·柯林斯   插畫: 理查·皮爾斯·雷納
音樂: 湯瑪斯·紐曼
服裝設計: 亞伯特·沃斯基
剪輯: 吉爾·比爾科克
{\fnMicrosoft YaHei\fs24\bord1\shad1\4a&H80&\pos(192,40)\b0藝術指導: 鄧尼斯·蓋斯納
Thanks, Mr. Miller.
謝謝  米勒先生
攝影: 康拉德·L·赫爾
執行製片: 沃爾特·F·帕克斯   瓊·布拉德肖
製片: 理查·D·紮努克   迪恩·紮努克   薩姆·門德斯
編劇: 大衛·塞歐夫
導演: 薩姆·門德斯
I'll help you with it later.
等一下我再教你
You go fetch your father.
去叫你爸下來
Pa?
爸
Dinner's ready.
吃晚餐了
Thank you.
謝謝
Bless us, O Lord, for thy gifts we are about to receive...
感謝主  賜予我們
...through the bounty of Jesus Christ, our Lord. Amen.
豐盛的食物與耶穌的愛  阿門
- Michael? - Sir?
- 麥克  - 什麼事  先生
It's a wake, so I don't want to see those dice.
我們是去參加喪禮  所以不准玩骰子
No, sir.
不會的  先生
Hello.
哈囉
I don't wanna go.
我不要去
- Come on, it's all right. - No. I'm scared.
- 走啦  沒關係  - 我會害怕
Ice helps preserve the body.
冰塊有助於保存屍體
So...
那麼
...who's got a hug for a lonely old man?
誰願意給孤單老人一個擁抱呢
Now then, which is which? Don't help me.
我來猜誰是誰  不要告訴我
- Peter and Michael. - No!
- 彼得和麥克  - 錯
Annie, Mike, good to see you.
安妮  麥克  你們好
- Did you bring the necessary? - Yes.
- 你帶吃飯的傢伙了嗎? - 帶了
If you'll excuse me, I have urgent business with these young gentlemen.
抱歉  我跟兩位小紳士有要事要商量
- Yeah! - Winner!
- 贏了  - 贏了
Call the cops! I know hustlers when I see them.
叫員警  你們耍老千
- I don't hustle, old-timer. - Pay the man.
- 沒有耍老千  老先生  - 付錢給他吧
Upstairs. Jacket pocket, in my study.
到樓上書房的外衣口袋拿
Before I change my mind.
快  免得我改變主意
- Hello? - Hello.
- 哈囉  - 哈囉
Remind me, which little Sullivan are you?
你是蘇利文的哪個兒子
- Michael, sir. - Sir? You don't have to call me sir.
- 麥克  先生  - 先生  不必叫我先生
I'm not your pa.
我不是你爸爸
No, Mr. Rooney.
不行  那叫隆尼先生好了
Call me Connor.
叫我康諾
No, call me Uncle Connor.
不  叫我康諾叔叔
What do you want?
你有什麼事
Mr. Rooney sent me to get his jacket.
隆尼先生叫我來拿外套
You come back later, huh?
等會再來  可以嗎
I'm busy.
我正在忙
Yes... Sir.
好的  先生
Hello, hello.
哈囉  哈囉
I want to welcome all of you to my home.
歡迎各位來到寒舍
It's good to have so many friends in this house again.
各位朋友齊聚一堂真叫我高興
Since Mary died, it's....
自從瑪麗死後
Well, it's just been me and my boy rattling around in these rooms.
只剩我和我兒子整日游走在這棟房子裡
I had this speech prepared, but it would be...
我原本準備了一篇講稿
...dishonest of me to say that I knew Danny well.
說我熟識丹尼可能不盡真實
But lose one of us, it hurts us all.
但任何人走了  大家都難過
I'll tell you what I do remember, though, and Finn will remember this too...
我來談談我記得的幾件事  相信芬恩也記得
...and that's Danny on the high school football team.
丹尼是高中橄欖球校隊的球員
A championship game. Down six points, 10 seconds left to play...
冠軍賽中  落後六分  只剩10秒
...four yards to go, Danny tackles his own quarterback.
還有四碼要攻  可丹尼卻擒倒了自家的四分衛
Mistakes, you know.... We all make them. God knows.
犯錯人人難免  上帝看在眼裡
Let's drink to Danny's honor.
為丹尼的榮耀喝一杯
Let's wake him to God and hope that he gets to heaven...
讓我們守護他進入天國
...at least an hour before the devil finds out he's dead.
在惡魔發現之前交到上帝手中
- Amen. - To Danny!
- 阿門  - 敬丹尼
And now, I would like to ask a dear and a trusted friend...
現在請我們忠心的老朋友
...Finn McGovern, to say a few words...
芬恩·麥高文跟我們講幾句話
...words that I'll wager got more poetry than mine.
他比我更善於表達
Get over here.
請過來這裡
Thank you, John.
謝謝你  約翰
"My brother Danny wasn't wise.
我的兄弟丹尼並不聰明
Nor was he gentle.
也並不溫柔體貼
And with a skinful of liquor in him, he was a pain in the ass.
三杯黃湯下肚  算得上是號麻煩人物
But he was loyal and brave.
但是  他忠貞不二勇敢無比
And he never told a lie.
終其一生未曾說謊
He'd have enjoyed this party.
他應該也會喜歡這次聚會
Me and the family, we wanna say thank you to our generous host.
我和其他家人想向你這位慷慨的主人道謝
Where would this town be without Mr. John Rooney?"
本鎮虧欠約翰·隆尼太多了
I've worked for you for many years now, John.
我為你效忠多年了  約翰
Nearly half my life.
幾乎是我的半輩子
And we've never had a disagreement.
我們從未有過爭執
I've come to realize that you rule this town...
我終於瞭解你的領導風格
...as God rules the earth.
簡直是人間的上帝
- You give, and you take away-- - Lovely. Lovely speech.
- 凡他賜予的終將回歸於他  - 太美了  講得太美了
I'm gonna bury my brother. Then I'm gonna deal with you.
等我安葬了兄弟  我再找你算帳
Sure, Finn, sure.
沒問題  芬恩
You'll take care of all of us.
我們大家都受你照顧
Once you get a good night's sleep.
先好好睡一覺
- He all right? - Yeah, he's fine.
- 他還好吧  - 還好
Just too much to drink.
只是喝多了
I'll talk to him.
我會找他談談
- Take Mike with you. - No, Pa--
- 帶麥克跟你一起去  - 不  爸
Take Mike with you.
帶麥克跟你一起去
Just talk, nothing more.
只是談談  沒別的事
Why are you always smiling?
為什麼你老是掛著笑臉呢
'Cause it's all so fucking hysterical.
因為這一切簡直瘋了
Michael.
麥克
What?
什麼
I had a nightmare. It was about Mr. Rooney's house.
我作了個惡夢  夢到隆尼先生的房子
It's just a house.
還不就是棟房子
A big house.
好大的房子
Go back to sleep.
回去睡覺
Is Mr. Rooney rich like the Babe?
隆尼先生和棒球巨星貝勃一樣有錢嗎
Richer.
比他更有錢
Are we rich?
我們有錢嗎
No, stupid.
當然不  傻瓜
What's papa's job?
爸爸的職業是什麼
He works for Mr. Rooney.
他替隆尼先生辦事
Why?
為什麼
Well, Papa didn't have a father...
爸爸沒有父親
...so Mr. Rooney looked after him.
所以隆尼先生照顧他
I know that, but what's his job?
這我知道  但他是做什麼的
He goes on missions for Mr. Rooney.
他幫隆尼先生解決問題
They're very dangerous. That's why he brings his gun.
因為很危險  所以他帶著槍
Sometimes even the president sends him on missions...
有時連總統都請他辦事
...'cause Papa was a war hero and all.
因為爸爸是個戰爭英雄
- You're just making that up. - I am not.
- 你亂講  - 是真的
It's all so fucking hysterical.
這一切簡直瘋了
Peter, I can't come to your concert tonight. I'm working.
彼得  我今晚不能參加你的音樂會  我得工作
Working at what?
做什麼
Putting food on your plate, young man.
讓你不必餓勝子  年輕人
All right, boys, come on, clear the plates.
好啦  小夥子們  收拾餐具
You're a good lad.
好孩子
- You want a shot? - No.
- 要不要來一口  - 不要
We're just talking to him, right?
我們只跟他談談  對吧
Sure.
當然
Don't get me wrong, Finn. I feel for you. I do.
別誤會  芬恩  我懂你的感受
You can't let a thing like that give you cause to go mouthing off.
但你沒必要含沙射影
You and my dad, you go back many years...
你跟我爸相識多年
...and he is a just man.
他是個可敬的人
So, what do you say?
你有什麼話要說嗎
Come on now, Finn.
表達點意見嘛  芬恩
Make this easy.
以免弄得太尷尬
We can't hear you.
我們聽不見
- All right. - Good.
- 就聽你們的  - 很好
Thank you.
謝謝你
I am sorry. I'm sorry for your loss. I'm sorry for this misunderstanding.
抱歉  抱歉你失去親人  抱歉引起這場誤會
And I'm sorry your brother was such a fucking liar.
很抱歉  你兄弟是個騙子
- My brother was not a liar. - Excuse me?
- 我兄弟不是騙子  - 你說什麼
To protect my family and keep my job, I'll stay quiet.
為了家人和飯碗  我會閉嘴
But don't think I don't know something's going on.
但我知道事有蹊蹺
- Don't think I won't find out what it is. - Whoa, buddy--
- 而且我一定會查出來  - 怎麼樣
Easy, easy.
別緊張
Easy.
We're just talking. You tell your father my brother never stole from him.
我們只是聊聊  跟你爸說  丹尼沒坑他的錢
I've checked the books. He never sold booze to no one. lt's all accounted for.
我查過帳冊  他沒有偷賣過一滴酒  每一桶都記得一清二楚
- If he sold it, where's the money? - Fuck should I know?
- 如果他賣了酒  那麼錢在哪  - 我怎麼知道
-Did you check his mattress? -Maybe you should check yours.
- 查查他床鋪底下  - 或許你該查查你自己的
There's something immoral here, don't you think, Mike?
他這什麼態度  麥克
My beloved father throws your undeserving little brother...
我父親幫你那不成材的弟弟
...the wake of his life, and this-- This is your thank-you?
辦個體面的喪禮  這就是你的謝意
- What a hideous world this is. - You think you're so smart.
- 這世界反啦  - 你自以為聰明
You think we don't know? You're spending so much time in Chicago--
以為我們不知道你在芝加哥混
What was that?
你怎麼那麼衝動
We're out of here.
快走
Jesus Christ, Connor, what the hell are you thinking?!
你到底在想什麼
Jesus.
噢  天呐
Michael.
麥克
Are you hurt?
你受傷了嗎
You saw everything?
你都看到了嗎
Jesus.
老天
You are not to speak of this to anyone. You understand?
這件事絕不可以說出去  懂嗎
Not to anyone!
誰都不准說
Who's this?
他是誰
It's one of yours?
你的孩子嗎
He must have been hiding in the car.
他一定是躲在車裡
Well, can he keep a secret?
他會保守秘密嗎
He's my son.
他是我兒子
Well, that's good enough for me.
那我就放心了
You take him home.
帶他回家吧
Think I'll walk.
我走路回去
Perfect night for a stroll.
今晚最適合散步
Does Mama know?
媽媽知道嗎
Your mother knows I love Mr. Rooney.
你媽媽知道我愛隆尼先生
We had nothing.
當我們一無所有時
He gave us a home, a life. We owe him.
他給了我們一個家  一份像樣的生活  我們虧欠他
Do you understand?
你懂嗎
你懂不懂
Yes.
懂
Well, come on inside, then.
進去吧
Boys, clear your plates, please.
孩子們  請收拾自己的碗盤
I'll do it later.
待會兒再收
- It's time for school now-- - It's only a plate!
- 要上學了  - 只不過是個盤子
What's he doing here?
他來做什麼
Michael was hiding in the car...
昨晚我出去時
...when I went out last night.
麥克躲在車裡
Jesus, Mike.
天啊  麥克
I've spoken to him. It won't happen again.
我跟他說過了  絕不再犯
Mom. Mom!
媽  媽
Just the feller...
正是你
Our secret, right?
我們之間的秘密  對吧
I'm talking about the dice.
我是說賭骰子
A man of honor always pays his debts.
君子有債必還
And keeps his word.
言出必行
I'm gonna be late for school.
我上學快遲到了
How is Michael? Is he okay?
麥克怎麼樣  他還好吧
I've spoken to him.
我跟他談過了
He understands.
他知道輕重
That's tough...
第一次看到這種事
...seeing that for the first time. Well, you turned out.
他一定相當震驚  不過  你已經熬過來了
You can't protect them forever.
你不可能永遠保護他們
If it wasn't this, it'd be something else.
他遲早會經歷這種事的
Natural law.
自然法則
Sons are put on this earth to trouble their fathers.
兒子生來就是替老子找麻煩
John's also made it clear that Finn McGovern's operation...
約翰交代得很清楚  芬恩·麥高文的地盤
...will be divided up locally...
將打散
...among two territories that John will select personally.
併入兩個約翰親自挑選的區域
I'd like to take this moment to thank Mr. Rance for...
在此特別感謝藍斯先生
...interrupting a busy travel schedule to pay us a visit.
百忙之中抽空前來
Thank you, Jack.
謝謝  傑克
Mr. Rance met with John and me earlier to make another bid...
藍斯先生跟約翰和我談過
...for our involvement in the unions.
他再次邀請我們加入工會
And I told Mr. Rance what I told him before:
我跟藍斯先生重申我的想法
What men do after work is what made us rich.
男人們下班後的活動讓我們賺飽了荷包
No need to screw them at work as well.
沒必要再去剝削他們的勞力
- Is there any other business? - Yes.
- 還有其他事情嗎  - 有
Connor, is there something you would like to say about last night?
康諾  昨晚的事報告一下
I'd like to apologize for what happened.
昨天的事  我想先道個歉
Especially to you, Pa.
特別是對你  爸
Two wakes in a month... What can I say?
一個月辦兩次喪事  我能說什麼呢
We lost a good man last night.
我們損失了一位好弟兄
You think it's funny?
你覺得好笑嗎
Try again.
重說一次
I'd like to apologize--
我想表達歉意
You would like to apologize? Try again.
你想表達歉意  重說
Gentlemen...
在座的各位
...my apologies.
謹致深深的歉意
Is everyone clear about bit borrowers?
各位清楚我們對小額貸款的立場了吧
There have been far too many debts outstanding.
欠債不還的人太多了
- Mike... - Just give me their names.
- 麥克  - 名單給我
Tell me who to visit.
跟我說該找誰
Thank you, gentlemen.
謝謝各位出席
Come on upstairs.
上樓來
我再也不跟別人打架
Mike.
麥克
Dad forgot to give you this.
爸忘了把這交給你
It's just a reminder for Tony Calvino. He's light again.
給湯尼·卡維諾的信函  他又拖欠債款了
Are you coming?
你來不來
No, I'm under house arrest for a while.
不  我暫時被禁足了
Look, I'm sorry about last night. I am.
昨晚的事我很抱歉  真的
I was... Yeah.
我本來  你知道的
All right.
沒關係
- Help you, sir? Or just looking? - Here to see Tony Calvino.
- 有什麼事嗎  先生  - 我來找湯尼·卡維諾
Yeah, and who are you?
是嗎  你是誰
Mike Sullivan.
麥克·蘇利文
Yes, sir.
沒問題  先生
You gonna frisk me?
要搜身嗎
- Should I? - It's a good idea.
-應該搜嗎  - 應該
That's the only one.
我只帶一把槍
I mean, I'm a grown man and this place is getting to me.
我不是小孩  這地方煩死了
Every night there's trouble.
每天晚上都有麻煩
No one's got no dough, but all the world's here wasting it.
全國人民都在遭罪  這裡的人卻揮霍無度
Always money for frills and twists, and never money for food.
有的人富得流油  穿華服  玩美女  有的人則窮得沒飯吃
Sometimes I despair the species, you know?
有時我真為人類感到悲哀
Number 12 in the beauty parlor. Who's the lucky face?
12號  幸運兒是哪位
I'm not from here originally, but jobs ain't hanging off trees, you know.
我不是本地人  但景氣這麼差  工作不會從天上掉下來
I'm a boxer by trade. Nine consecutive titles.
我是拳擊手  連獲九次冠軍
That's a record in South Orange.
破了南橘市的記錄
I'd make a pretty good bodyguard, I think.
當保鏢我想不成問題
What I'm saying is, is Mr. Rooney looking for anyone?
我是說  隆尼先生缺人手嗎
You know, anyone like me, for example? Is there any chance you might ask him?
比方說  我這種人  有機會問問他嗎
- Sure. - Thank you, Mr. Sullivan.
- 當然  - 謝謝  蘇利文先生
Thank you very much. I appreciate it.
真是太感謝你了
Mr. Calvino? Mr. Calvino, Mike Sullivan's here.
卡維諾先生  卡維諾先生  麥克·蘇利文來訪
- Shit. - He wants to see you.
- 糟了  - 他想見你
- Shit. Is he packing? - Not anymore.
- 完了  他帶著槍嗎  - 被我拿走了
All right.
好吧
Show him in.
帶他進來
Hey, hey, hey. You stick around, okay?
你留在我身邊  好嗎
Hey!
喂
How the hell are you? Things good with the old man?
什麼風把你吹來了  老先生還好吧
Yeah.
是的
What brings you here? Don't imagine it's the pussy.
什麼事竟麻煩你親自上門  該不是來找樂子的吧
- I have a letter for you from Mr. Rooney. - Am I behind again?
- 隆尼先生有封信要給你  - 我付款又晚了嗎
- Am I in trouble? - I don't know.
- 我惹上麻煩了嗎  - 我不知道
殺了蘇利文  舊帳一筆勾消
Michael.
麥克
No!
不
No! My God!
不  老天
- Pa, I'm sorry. - Stupid!
- 爸  對不起  - 笨蛋
The kid would've talked. I'm sorry.
那小鬼一定會說出去  對不起
Goddamn you. Goddamn you!
上帝詛咒你  上帝詛咒你
I curse the fucking day you were born!
我詛咒你出生的那一天
I curse it!
我詛咒它
You!
你
Oh, Lord.
噢  主啊
Oh, Lord. God help us.
噢  主啊  上帝保佑我們
God help us.
上帝保佑我們
This house is not our home anymore.
這房子不再是我們的家了
It's just an empty building.
它只是空蕩蕩的屋子
All right, you stay here. You stay out of sight.
你留在這兒  不要讓人發現
- Don't go, Pa. Don't go. - Michael...
- 不要走  爸  別走  - 麥克
...when they find out we're gone, they're gonna come after us.
他們發現我們走了一定會追來
I have to protect you now.
現在起  我必須保護你
Please, Pa.
我求你  爸
All right, here, take this.
好吧  這個拿著
- No. I don't want it. - Take it.
- 我不要  - 拿去
- I don't want it. - Boy, take it! You got six shots.
- 我不要啊  - 拿著  你有六發子彈
If I'm not back in half an hour, go tell Reverend Lynch what's happened.
我如果半個小時沒回來  去找林奇牧師說出實情
Do not go to Father Callaway.
不要找卡拉威神父
I don't have any business with you, Mr. Kelly.
此事跟你無關  凱利先生
But I have business with you, Mike.
但我有事找你  麥克
Go ahead.
請說
What is that?
那是什麼東西
25,000 dollars. Mr. Rooney wants you to know there's more if you need it.
二萬五千美元  隆尼先生說  需要的話還有
You have friends in lreland, Mike. Why don't you take Peter and leave?
你在愛爾蘭有朋友  帶著彼得遠走高飛吧
I can't take Peter.
我沒辦法帶彼得去
He's dead.
他死了
- So where's Connor? - He's in hiding.
- 康諾在哪裡  - 躲起來了
- Where? - You know I can't tell you that.
- 躲在哪裡  - 你知道我不能說
You think sticking a gun to my head is gonna make any difference to me?
你以為拿槍對著我有用嗎
If I tell you, I'm a dead man anyway. We both are.
說出來  我還不是死路一條  我們兩個都一樣
Think, Mike. Don't be stupid. I'm just the messenger.
想清楚  麥克  別做傻事  我只是負責傳話
Then give Mr. Rooney a message for me.
那麼幫我帶句話給隆尼先生
What is it?
什麼話
Give me the gun.
槍給我
Where are we going?
我們要去哪裡
To Chicago.
芝加哥
There's a man there who runs things.
我認識那裡的一位元大人物
I've done some work for him.
以前幫他辦過幾次事
We have to find out where he stands.
我們得請教他的意見
Try to get some sleep.
你先睡一會
I want you to wait for me here.
你在這裡等我
- Sure. - I won't be long. You'll be all right?
- 當然  - 我很快回來  沒問題吧
- Yeah, I'll be all right. - That's a good boy.
- 沒問題  - 好孩子
- Hello, Mike. - Hello, fellas.
- 哈囉  麥克  - 哈囉  兩位
It's nice to see you. We heard what happened. How you holding up?
又見面了,我們聽說了,你還撐得住吧?
I need to talk to Mr. Nitti.
我想跟尼提先生談談
- He's awful busy. - I can wait.
- 他非常忙  - 我可以等
Okay. Take the man to the top.
好  帶這位先生去頂樓
Certainly, sir.
當然  先生
Sorry to make you wait so long, Mike. Come on in.
抱歉讓你久等  麥克  請進
We all just heard what happened.
我們剛聽說了你的事
Jesus, I'm sorry, Mike.
天啊  真遺憾  麥克
Well, thank you for seeing me, Mr. Nitti.
謝謝你肯見我  尼提先生
Come on, sit down.
請坐
- Like some coffee or...? - No.
- 來杯咖啡還是  - 不用了
- You sure? - Yes, thank you.
- 你確定嗎  - 是的 謝謝
So, what can I do for you, Mike?
我能怎麼幫你  麥克
I'd like to work for you.
我想為你工作
Well, that's very interesting.
這倒有趣
And in return, I'd like you to turn a blind eye to what I have to do.
作為回報  我希望您不要干涉我的私事
And what is that?
你想怎麼做
Kill the man who murdered my family.
宰了殺我妻兒的兇手
Is one more body gonna make a difference?
多死一個人有什麼不一樣嗎
This is a good proposal, Mr. Nitti.
這份提議對你很有利  尼提先生
I will work only for you, and you know I can do a good job.
我只為你工作  我是個中高手
I respect you, Mike. I do.
我尊敬你  麥克  真的
We would like nothing more than to have you come work for us. But not like this.
我巴不得你為我效命  但不是在這種情況之下
What you're asking me is impossible.
你的要求根本不可能
Is it?
是嗎
Let me explain something to you that maybe you haven't realized.
讓我為你解釋清楚  或許有些事情你不瞭解
All these years, you've been living under the protection...
多年來  許多關心你的人
...of people who care about you.
一直在保護著你
And those same people are protecting you now, including me.
同一批人現在還在保護你  包括我
So if you go ahead with this, if you open that door...
如果你一意孤行  打開那扇門
...you're walking through it alone.
你得孤獨地走下去
And all that loyalty, all that trust, will no longer exist for you.
所謂的忠誠  信任  對你來說不再存在
And Mike, you won't make it. Not on your own.
而且  麥克  你不可能成功  單槍匹馬不可能
And not with a little boy.
帶著小孩更不可能
You're protecting him already?
你已經開始保護他了吧
We're protecting our interests, Mike.
我們是在保護我們的利益
I drove all through the night to see you.
我連夜驅車前來找你
I appreciate that. Now I suggest you drive yourself back.
謝謝  我建議你再趕回去
Go home, Mike. Go home and bury your wife and child.
回家吧  麥克  好好安葬妻小
With our blessing.
我們祝福你
It won't be that simple.
事情沒那麼簡單
You heard?
你們聽到了吧
Dad, listen to me. He's in the building.
爸爸  聽我說  趁他在這裡
- You can end this now. Take him now. - Connor, get upstairs.
- 你可以做個了結  殺了他  - 康諾  上樓去
God help me.
上帝幫幫我
God help me. What do I do?
上帝幫幫我  我該怎麼辦
You think objectively.
客觀地想清楚
And you make your choice.
然後做出抉擇
What would you do if Sullivan were just some guy?
如果蘇利文是個陌生人  你會怎麼辦
God help me.
上帝幫幫我
- Make it quick. - And the kid?
- 一定要乾淨俐落  - 那孩子呢
Oh, Christ. No, no.
噢  老天  不  不
One day the kid becomes a man... Think he won't remember?
你以為他長大後會忘記嗎
I said not the kid.
我說了  不能殺那小孩
All right.
好的
I know who to call.
我知道該找誰
There's a guy who's done some work for us in the past.
一個過去幫過我們的人
He's gifted.
他極具天賦
Excuse me, ma'am. Press. Press.
抱歉  女士  我是媒體記者  媒體記者
He was raping my wife. He raped my wife.
他強暴我太太
Come on, come on, you're treading on the evidence here.
跟我來  你踩到證物了
Two minutes.
只要兩分鐘
You got it, Mr. Maguire.
沒問題  馬蓋爾先生
Harlen Maguire. Good evening, Mr. Nitti.
哈倫·馬蓋爾  晚安  尼提先生
Sixteen hundred.
一千六百美元
Sixteen hundred dollars is my rate, Mr. Nitti.
我的價碼是一千六  尼提先生
And what I make on the photographs is mine.
照片是我自己賺的外快
No, never met him.
沒見過他
But I know his work.
但聽說過他的傑作
He traveling alone?
他獨來獨往嗎
How old?
多大年紀
What do I do with the kid?
小孩怎麼處理
Will do.
就照你的意思
Thank you.
謝謝
You remember your aunt Sarah? Your mom's sister?
你記得莎拉姨媽嗎  你母親的姐姐
She lives in Perdition. She'll take you in.
住在派迪遜  她肯讓你跟她住
Where is it?
她家在哪裡
Right by the lake.
湖邊
We went there once, all of us, when you were 4, maybe 5.
我們全家去過一次  你四五歲的時候
It's beautiful.
風景很美
You remember?
記得嗎
The place with the dog.
她家有狗
- Hello? - Sarah.
- 哈囉  - 莎拉
Mike. Oh, thank God.
麥克  噢  感謝上帝
I want you to know we're okay.
只是跟你報個平安
Where are you?
你在哪裡
We're on our way to your place, if that's all right.
正在去你家的路上  如果可以的話
Of course. I'll be back there in two days.
當然  我兩天后回去
How's Michael?
麥克還好嗎
He's all right.
他還好
How was it?
喪事辦得怎麼樣
Oh, Mike...
噢  麥克
Hello?
哈囉
We'll see you soon.
見面再談
- Hello, operator? - Yes, sir.
- 哈囉  接線生  - 是的  先生
I was just cut off, could you reconnect me?
剛斷線了  麻煩幫我重接
You hungry?
肚子餓嗎
No.
不餓
Might not be another diner for a while, so you should eat.
前面可能很遠都不會再有餐館
I'm not hungry.
我不餓
I just wanna read.
我只想看書
- Slow night, huh? - You kidding? This is busy.
- 生意挺清淡的嘛  - 開玩笑  算忙了
- What can I get you? - You got a special?
- 要點什麼  - 有特餐嗎
Everything's special.
每樣東西都很特別
- Is that so? - Everything except the food.
- 是嗎  - 除了食物以外
Everything except the food?
除了食物以外都很特別
- You ought to be on the stage. - Don't I know it.
- 你應該從事演藝工作  - 可不是嘛
Give me some of that honey-dipped fried chicken and a black coffee.
我要蜜汁炸雞和一杯黑咖啡
Duck soup.
馬上來
Don't mind me, sir.
不用理我  先生
It's a free country. Used to be, anyhow.
這是自由國度  曾經是啦
No, thank you, sir.
不  謝謝你  先生
Is that your profession or your pleasure?
那是你的職業還是消遣
Both, I guess.
應該說兩者皆是
To be paid to do what you love.... Ain't that the dream?
既喜愛又有錢賺  豈不完美
I guess so.
說得沒錯
Yourself?
你呢
I'm a salesman. Machine parts.
銷售員  機械零件
Machine parts.
機械零件
- That's wonderful. - I assure you, it is not.
- 好工作  - 跟你說  一點都不好
- So who do you work for? - Can you keep a secret?
- 你在什麼公司上班  - 可以幫我保守秘密嗎
I'm press.
我是媒體記者
Which paper?
哪家報社
All over. I'm something of a rarity.
很多家  我從事的是罕見的工作
How's that?
怎麼說
I shoot the dead.
我幫死人照相
Dead bodies, that is. I don't kill them.
屍體啦  人不是我殺的
I should hope not.
我想應該不是吧
Always fascinated me, the look of them, you know?
死人的樣子令我很著迷  有點奇怪吧
- You ever seen one? - Yeah.
- 你見過死人嗎  - 見過
Sorry for you.
我為你感到難過
Terrible thing.
恐怖的經驗
But it sure makes you feel alive, don't it?
但讓你感覺活著真好  不是嗎
I'll drink to that.
值得為此幹一杯
Stuff makes you sweat, huh?
它令你直冒汗呢
Yeah, piss too.
對  是啊  而且利尿
Excuse me, ma'am, can you help me out here?
對不起  小姐  洗手間在哪
Just through here.
從這裡走過去
Hey!
喂
Look out, there.
小心
- Thanks, Ruby. - Good night.
- 謝謝你  露比  - 晚安
Forgot to leave a tip.
忘了放小費了
- Get down. - Why? What's going on?
- 趴下  - 為什麼  怎麼回事
Get down!
趴下
Hey, what do you think you're--?
嘿  你在幹什麼
Get out of the car.
下車
Get out of the car! When I say get down, you get down.
出來  我說趴下就趴下
Don't ask questions. When I say we're stopping to eat, you stay with me.
沒有為什麼  吃東西時  一定得跟在我身邊
You listen to me from now on, or you start taking care of yourself.
聽話  不然你得自己照顧自己
I can take care of myself fine! You never wanted me along anyway.
我可以照顧自己  反正你根本不想帶著我
- You think it's my fault this happened. - Stop it.
- 你認為這全是我的錯  - 住口
It was not your fault!
那不是你的錯
None of this is your fault.
所有事情都不是你的錯
- Just take me to Aunt Sarah's. - I can't take you there.
- 帶我去莎拉阿姨家就對了  - 我不能帶你去那兒
Not now.
現在不行
- Why? - He knows that's where we're going.
- 為什麼  - 他知道我們要去那裡
So, what are you gonna do?
那你想怎麼辦
Something I can't do alone.
接下來的事我一個人辦不成
You have to listen to me now, okay?
你一定要好好聽我的話  知道嗎
Or else both of us are dead.
不然我們兩個都活不了
I have to make Capone give up Connor.
我得逼卡彭放棄康諾
There's one thing Chicago loves more than anything...
現在芝加哥幫派份子只關心一樣東西
...and that's their money.
錢
They've got it in banks all over the state. We have to find it and take it.
他們將錢存在州內各銀行  我們把它找出來  拿走
- Are you gonna help me? - Yes.
- 你要幫我嗎  - 好
Then I have to teach you something.
那麼我就要教你幾樣功夫
- You know what the clutch is? - Sure I know what the clutch is.
- 知不知道什麼是離合器  - 當然知道
- What is the clutch? - The clutch, it... It clutches.
- 離合器是什麼  - 就離合器嘛  幫助離合
Right, it clutches. Which of those pedals is the clutch?
對  幫助離合  哪一個踏板是離合器
That's the gas.
那是油門
Gas. I'll show you.
加速的油門
There. Right there, see?
我來教你  看到沒
There's the clutch, and it does the clutching.
離合器幫助你進檔  退檔
Let's go again.
再來一次
Release gas, clutch, shift gear, hit gas...
松油門  踩離合器  換檔  踩油門
Shift.
換檔
- Can I make one suggestion? - No.
- 我可以給你個建議嗎  - 不用
I'm doing this.
我要自己做
Hey, 45 miles an hour, that's a little fast.
時速45英里  太快了
Look out for the tractor, Mike.
小心那輛牽引機  麥克
Michael, look out for the tractor.
麥克  小心那輛牽引機
Watch out for the tractor. Watch out for the tractor!
小心那輛牽引機  小心那輛牽引機
- We made it. - Oh, yeah, yeah, we made it.
- 我們成功了  - 對  對  成功了
No more excuses. I've told you once, now I'm telling you again--
沒有理由  我不再說了
- I'm looking for a Mr. McDougal. -Just one moment.
- 我找麥道格先生  - 請稍等
Well, this is a pleasant surprise.
真是意外的驚喜
I wasn't expecting another deposit until the end of the month.
我以為這個月不會有存款了
Actually, I'm making a withdrawal. I want dirty money only.
事實上  我是來取款的  我只拿髒錢
Everything you're holding for Capone that's off the books. Open the safe.
卡彭的每一分錢都不能少  保險櫃打開
You're insane. You know they'll find out who you are.
你瘋了  他們一定知道你是誰
The name's Sullivan. You want me to spell it?
大名蘇利文  要我寫下來嗎
Open the box.
箱子打開
They'll kill you. They're animals.
他們會殺了你  他們是野獸
You don't say. Put it in.
是嗎  放進去
That's for you.
這疊是給你的
Call it a handling charge. Tell Chicago I took it.
算手續費  跟芝加哥說我拿的
But if I read about this in the papers, if I read about the savings of farmers...
但如果我在報上看到無辜農夫的血汗錢
...being wiped out by a heartless bank robber, I won't be happy.
被搶匪搶走  我會不高興
Good afternoon.
午安
You really trust me not to say anything?
相信我不會供出你嗎
Always trust a bank manager.
銀行經理最值得信賴
There's no rush.
你還真慢條斯理
- Coffee? - Thank you.
- 咖啡  - 謝謝
So, what brings you guys to the middle of nowhere?
怎麼會來這鳥不生蛋的地方
We're bank robbers.
我們是銀行搶匪
We're just passing through.
只是路過
So when do I get my share of the money?
我的那份什麼時候給我
Well, how much do you want?
你要多少
Two hundred dollars.
兩百美元
Okay. Deal.
沒問題  說定了
- Could I have had more? - You'll never know.
- 我如果多要  你會給我嗎  - 天機不可洩漏
Come on, come on.
快接啊
How much did they take?
他們拿走了多少
How much?
多少
Okay, answer me this: What are we paying you for?
回答我  我們付錢給你幹嘛的
- Where's my father? - What's this?
- 我父親呢  - 搞什麼
Why is no one talking to me? I feel like a fucking prisoner.
沒人願意跟我說話嗎  好像我是個犯人
I told you. You are not a prisoner. You are being protected.
你不是犯人  你在戒護中
- This is what your father wants. - I can look after myself.
- 令尊交代的  - 我會照顧自己
No, you can't. This is the point.
不  你不會  這就是重點
You're a big baby who doesn't know his thumb from his dick.
你連拇指跟老二都分不清楚
Fuck you.
去你的
The only reason you're still alive is because you're John Rooney's son.
聽清楚  小子  要不是你爹  你能活到現在嗎
You're being a little shortsighted here, Frank.
別太短視近利  法蘭克
My father is an old man.
我爸是個老頭
I am the future.
而我是未來
So don't you ever talk to me that way again.
不要用那種態度跟我說話
Maguire, do what you have to. Find them.
馬蓋爾  想辦法把他們找出來
I'm sorry, Mr. Sullivan, there is no money.
對不起  蘇利文先生  沒有錢
No-- I can get you money, I just--
我是說  我可以幫你弄錢
It won't be Chicago's.
但  不是芝加哥的錢
They took it all out two days ago.
他們兩天前提光了
- Who authorized it? - The accountant.
- 誰授權的  - 會計師
What's his name?
叫什麼名字?
This is Mr. Rance in the bridal suite.
我是蜜月套房的藍斯先生
Before you proffer your congratulations, there's no Mrs. Rance with me...
不用虛情假意的道賀  這裡沒有藍斯太太
...and I'm all the better for it. Listen carefully...
我很慶倖  你仔細聽好
...because I am in no mood.
我心情不好
I'm going to say this only once.
我只說一次
I would like a boiled egg, and I want it runny.
我要水煮蛋  蛋黃半熟
Pa, can we sleep in a motel room tonight instead of the car?
爸  我們可以睡汽車旅館  而不是睡車上嗎
Yeah, that would be nice.
好啊  這主意不錯
How many more days you gonna want me, mister?
你還要我陪你幾天  先生
Can't we close the curtains, even for a little while?
窗簾可以拉上嗎  就一會兒
I can't get no sleep with all that light.
這麼亮我睡不著
You see anything, you hit that horn twice.
發現任何異狀  按兩次喇叭
Don't get out of the car, no matter what.
絕對不要下車
Bye.
再見
- Ready? - I'm ready.
- 準備好了嗎  - 好了
Yes, sir. Right away, sir.
是的  先生  馬上
Runny.
半熟
It's open.
門沒鎖
Top marks for speed, no marks for cookery.
速度一流  品質不入流
What, may I ask, do you call this?
請問這叫做什麼
Put it down.
放下
- Mr. Sullivan. - Mr. Rance.
- 蘇利文先生  - 藍斯先生
How did you find me?
你怎麼找到我的
This is the best hotel in the area. And you are so very...particular.
這是本區最高級的飯店  而你總是那麼特別
Yes, indeed, Mr. Sullivan.
說得沒錯  蘇利文先生
May I ask you to lower your weapon.
可以放下武器嗎
Thank you. Now, what do you want?
謝謝  有何貴幹
Information.
情報
I can't give you the files.
資料不能給你
All right, all right.
好  好
They're in the next room.
東西在隔壁房間
- In here. - Bring it in.
- 在這裡  - 拿過來
I can't see.
我看不見
What will you accomplish by interfering with our business?
你干涉我們的買賣有何意義
- This has nothing to do with business. - It's all business. You fail to grasp that.
- 此事跟買賣無關  - 怎麼會無關  只是你不瞭解
And in business, you must have something to trade.
所謂買賣  一定得有東西交換
And you, Mr. Sullivan, have nothing to trade.
你  蘇利文先生  沒東西交換
Especially not for anyone as valuable as Connor Rooney.
尤其是交換昂貴的康諾·隆尼
I don't understand.
我不懂
Opening bell on Wall Street.
華爾街開盤了
Come on, open it.
打開
Which one is it?
哪把鑰匙來著
No, no, not it.
不對  不對  不是這把
Tried that one already.
這把試過了
Better start over.
最好重試一次
You got one more try.
你只剩一次機會
There it is.
噢  找到了
I'm okay. Watch the road!
我還好  專心看路
Pa! Pa, are you okay?
爸  爸  你還好嗎
Pa!
爸
Help!
救命
Help us!
救救我們
Help!
救命
救命啊
Help us!
救救我們
When are you two heading out?
你們兩個什麼時候離開
We've stayed long enough.
我知道打擾你們很久了
We don't wanna cause you any trouble.
我不想為您惹來麻煩
No trouble so far.
目前還沒有麻煩
He's a good worker.
他是個好幫手
You have any kids?
你有孩子嗎
No.
沒有
We met too late.
我們相識得太晚
He dotes on you.
他非常愛你
You don't see it.
你沒有注意到
Hello.
哈囉
I had a bad dream.
我作了一個惡夢
You wanna talk about it?
想說給我聽嗎
Well, come on in. Take a seat...
進來吧  坐下聊聊
...if you want.
如果你想的話
Math, huh?
你在算數學嗎
Yeah.
對
I always hated it.
我最討厭數學
Me too.
我也是
So, what do you like?
那你喜歡什麼
Huh?
什麼
What subjects do you like--? Did you like...in school?
你在學校的時候  喜歡什麼科目
Bible history, maybe.
聖經歷史  可能吧
Why?
為什麼
I like the stories.
我喜歡那些故事
Peter was good at math.
彼得數學很厲害
Was he?
是嗎
Did you like Peter more than me?
你是不是更喜歡彼得  而不是我
No.
不會啊
No, Michael.
不會啦  麥克
I loved you both the same.
你們兩個我都愛
But you were...
但是  你
You were different with me.
對我不一樣
Was I?
是嗎
Well...
嗯
Maybe it was because Peter was just such a sweet boy, you know?
可能因為彼得比較可愛
And you...
而你
You were more like me.
你比較像我
And I didn't want you to be.
而我並不希望你像我
I didn't mean to be...different.
我不是有意  偏心
Okay.
好吧
Good night, Pa.
晚安  爸
Good night.
晚安
芬恩·麥高文之帳戶
康諾·隆尼之存款收據
Michael, wake up. Get your things.
麥克  醒醒  收拾行李
We're leaving.
我們要走了
We left you something.
我們留了點東西給你們
Hello, John.
你好  約翰
You're a smart man, Michael.
你真不簡單  麥克
I wanna talk.
我想跟你談談
Here?
在這兒嗎
Downstairs.
樓下
I didn't think I'd see you again.
沒想到還會再見面
Read this.
拿去看看
Connor's been stealing from you for years.
康諾偷你的錢好幾年了
He keeps accounts open under the names of dead men. Men like the McGoverns.
他用死人的名義開通了帳戶  比如說麥高文家人
I stood there and helped him kill Finn to line his own pockets.
我幫他殺了芬恩  沒想到卻是在幫他賺黑心錢
I thought I was working for you, but I wasn't.
我以為我替你工作  其實不然
You think I'd give up my son?
你以為我會放棄我兒子嗎
He was betraying you.
他背叛了你
I know.
我知道
Now, listen to me.
聽我說
I tried to avoid more bloodshed. You wouldn't accept that...
我曾嘗試避免流血  可你不接受
...so I did what was necessary. But I've always loved you like a son.
那我只能下狠手  但我一直把你當兒子看
And now I'm telling you, leave before it's too late.
現在我警告你  趁來得及  快走
Think.
想一想
They're protecting him now, but when you're gone, they won't need him.
他們目前保護他  但當你走後  他們就不再需要他了
- This ends with Connor dead regardless. - That may be...
- 康諾橫豎是死路一條  - 很可能如此
...but you are asking me...
但你是要求我
...to give you the key to his room so you can walk in...
把他的房間鑰匙給你
...put a gun to his head and pull the trigger. I can't do that.
讓你用槍射穿他腦袋  我辦不到
- He murdered Annie and Peter. - There are only murderers in this room.
- 他謀殺了安妮和彼得  - 這裡哪一個不是殺人兇手
Michael, open your eyes.
麥克  張開眼睛看清楚
This is the life we chose, the life we lead.
我們選擇了這種生活  就得過這種生活
And there is only one guarantee: None of us will see heaven.
只有一項保證  我們誰都上不了天堂
Michael could.
麥克可以
Then do everything that you can to see that that happens.
那麼  你就盡你所能確定你能達成心願
Leave. I'm begging you.
走吧  我求你
It's the only way.
這是唯一的路
And if I go?
如果我真的走呢
Then...
那麼
...I will mourn...
我將哀悼
...the son I lost.
我的喪子之痛
What are you gonna do?
你想做什麼
Just one last thing, and then it's done.
再做一件事就全部了結了
Go back to bed, Michael.
回去睡覺
給麥克
I'm glad it's you.
我很慶倖是你
I understand.
我瞭解
But then Al wants your assurance that after that, it's over.
但艾爾希望你保證這件事之後  一了百了
The Lexington Hotel, room 1432.
萊辛頓飯店  1432房
Is that the house?
就是那棟房子嗎
That's it.
沒錯
I knew there was a dog.
我就知道有一隻狗
Sarah? It's me, Mike. We're here.
莎拉  是我  麥克  我們到了
Smile.
笑一個
Give me the gun.
把槍給我
Michael.
麥克
Michael...
...don't you do this.
不要開槍
Give me the gun, Michael.
把槍給我  麥克
Come on.
快點
Give me the gun.
把槍給我
I couldn't do it.
我下不了手
I know.
我知道
- Pa. - I'm sorry.
- 爸  - 對不起
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
對不起  對不起
I'm sorry.
對不起
Pa.
爸
Pa!
Pa.
爸
Pa! Pa!
爸  爸
I saw then that my father's only fear...
我看見父親唯一的恐懼
...was that his son would follow the same road.
就是兒子步上他的後塵
And that was the last time I ever held a gun.
那是我最後一次拿槍
People always thought I grew up on a farm.
人們以為我在農場長大
And I guess, in a way, I did.
而我想  從某方面來看  這也沒錯
But I lived a lifetime before that...
但在那之前的六周逃亡路上
...in those six weeks on the road...
我經歷了我的整個人生
...in the winter of 1931.
當時是1931年冬天
When people ask me if Michael Sullivan was a good man...
當別人問我  麥克·蘇利文是不是個好人
...or if there was just no good in him at all...
或者  他是不是無惡不作
...I always give the same answer.
我的答案永遠一樣
I just tell them...
我只跟他們說
..."He was my father."
他是我父親
謹以本片深沉紀念
康 拉 德 · L · 赫 爾
生於1926年  卒於2003年
康拉德·L·赫爾  本片攝影指導  這是他生前最後一部掌鏡電影